I want you to come quick.
ازت ميخوام که سريعتر بياي
Don't go!
!نرو
Edward Lanman was sitting in his pleasant house in London
ادوارد لنمن توي خونه قشنش در لندن نشسته
The sun was shining It was an early morning in June, not quite...
خورشيد داشت ميدرخشيد ...يه صبح زود در ماه جون بود , نه تماما
Iris.
آيريس
Iris, wait for me.
آيريس , منتظرم بمون
Just keep tight hold of me and it'll be all right.
فقط نزديک من باش و همه ي خوب ميشه
-You won't keep still. -I can't keep still.
نميتوني ساکت باشي نميتونم ساکت باشم
I can't catch up with you.
نميتونم بهت برسم
-Iris, you've got bicycle oil on your ankle. -I don't care, John.
آيريس , روي قوزکت روغن دورخه ريخته اهميتي نميدم , جان
Those of you, our guests...
...آنهايي از شما , ميهمانان
... on whose magnificent generosity we depend...
سخاوت باشکوهي که ما بهش تکيه ميکنيم
...we really are most frightfully grateful...
ما جدا به شدت ساسذاريم
...will need no introduction to one of our most distinguished graduates...
به مقدمه يني احتياج نداره که يکي از برجسته ترين فارغ التحصيلان ما
... an honorary fellow, Dame Iris Murdoch.
يه شخص افتخاري , ديم آيريس موردوک
She's a noted philosopher as well as author of some twenty-six novels.
اون يه فيلسوف برجسته و همنين نويسنده 26 رمانه
And we are honoured to have her with us today.
و امروز ما مفتخريم که ايشون همراه ما هستند
As well as the distinguished Warton Professor of Literature..
"همنين روفسور ادبيات برجسته"وارتن
...who has the great good fortune of being married to her.
که شانس بسيار بزري داشته که با ايشون ازدواج کرده
I need say no more about her.
لازمه ديه درموردش نم
For good wine needs no bush.
ون يز خوب نياز به معرفي نداره
But she will not mind comparison with...
...اما اون فکرشو نميکنه مقايسه شه با
... say, a really fine vintage claret.
مثلا , با يه شراب عالي درجه 1
... Dame Iris will speak to you about the importance of education.
ديم آيريس درباره اهميت تحصيلات با شما صحبت ميکنه
Education doesn't make you happy. And nor does freedom.
تحصيلات شما رو خوشحال نميکنه و يا آزاد نميکنه
We don't become happy just because we're free -- if we are...
ما خوشحال نميشيم فقط بخاطر اينکه ما آزاذيم . ار باشيم
... or because we've been educated, if we have.
يا براي اينکه ما تحصيل کرده ايم اه کرده ايم
But because education may be the means...
اما براي اينکه تحصيلات ممکنه راهي باشه
... by which we realise we are happy.
که ما بفهميم خوشحاليم
It opens our eyes, our ears.
اون شمامونو وا ميکنه , وشهامونو
Tells us where delights are lurking.
به ما ميه کجا خوشي ها کمين کرده
Convinces us that there is only one freedom...
ما رو متقاعد ميکنه که فقط يه آزادي
... of any importance whatsoever.
مهمي وجود داره
That of the mind.
اون ذهن ماست
And gives us the assurance,the confidence...
و اون به ما دلرمي  و اعتماد ميده
...to walk the path our mind, our educated mind offers.
که توي راه ذهنمون, ذهن تحصيل کرده مون قدم بزنيم
I shall tell him all my love.
بايد تمام علايقم رو بهش بم
All my soul's adoration.
تمام ستايش هاي روحم
And I think he will hear me.
وفکر کنم که اون بهم وش ميده
And will not say me nay.
و هرز به من نه نميه
It is this that gives my soul.
اين خودشه که روحمو فدا کرده
All it's joyous elation.
تمامش احساس غرور و شادمانيه
As I hear the sweet larks sing.
همانطور که آوار کاوکهاي شيرين رو ميشنوم
In the clear air of the day.
در يک روز اک
Yes, of course there's something fishy...
آره , البته يه يز مشکوکي وجود داره
... about describing people's feelings.
درباره وصف کردن احساسات مردم
Try hard to beaccurate, but...
سخت کار ميکنه تا دقيق باشه, اما
... as soon as you start to define such and such a feeling...
همينکه شروع ميکني به تعريف کردن ازقبيل
... language let's you down.
زبان احساس , روت رو زمين ميندازه
When we really speak the truth, words are insufficient.
وقتي ما واقعا درباره حقيقت صحبت ميکنيم الفاظ ناکافيه
Almost everything, except things like "pass the gravy" ...
تقريبا همه يز "به جز "عبور از کارهاي غيرقانوني
... is a lie of a sort. And that being the case, I shall shut up.
که يه وضع ناجوريه و اون موردي ميشه که , بايد خفه شم
And pass the gravy.
و عبور از کارهاي قانوني
But love, or at least unsatisfied love...
اما عشق , يا حداقل عشق ناراضي
... is concerned as much with understanding.
به حد قابل فهم مضطربه
And real love, extreme love...
و عشق واقعي , نهايت عشق
... once it's recognised has stamp of the indubitable...
يه مرتبه به مهر بي شکي شناخته ميشه
Ah, John, may I call you, John, may I?
آه جان , ميشه بهت زن بزنم , جان ميتونم؟
Meet Miss Murdoch.
با خانم موردوک ملاقات کن
Iris, my dear, John Bayley.
آيريس ,عزيزم , جان بايلي
One of the more promising young lecturers in the English School.
يکي از اميد بحش ترين سخنرانان جوان در مدرسه انليسي
Though I caught him out over Old English grammar, his weaker side I fear.
فکر کردم براي هميشه از راه به درش کردم دستور زبان انليسي قديم ,طرف ضعيفشه که من ميترسم
A minor question of Anglo-Saxon syntax.
تحقيق جزئي نحوه ترکيب آنلوساکسن
Wine!
!شراب
I mean...
...منظورم
... It went down the wrong way.
بد رفت ايين
Yes, I like that.
بله , ازش خوشم مياد
There is a right way down, of course.
البته يه راه درست هضم وجود داره
Amazing how most of us find it without even thinking about it.
شفت آوره که طور بيشتر ماها اونو يدا ميکنيم حتي بدون فکر کردن به اون
I rarely think...
...اهي اوقات فکر ميکنم
If you think about it, you'll never find it.
اه بهش فکر کني , هرز نميتوني يداش کني
Best thing to do is hang on and trust the body. I do.
بهترين کار اينه که يه دقيقه وايسي و به بدنت اعتماد کني,من کردم
Human beings love each other.
آدما عاشق همديه ميشن
In sex, in friendship...
توي سکس , رفاقت
... and when they're in love.
و موقعيه که اونا عاشق شدن
And they cherish other beings.
و اونا به موجودات ديه احترام ميذارن
Humans, animals, plants - even stones.
انسانها , حيوانات , ياهان - حتي سنها
The quest for happiness and the promotion of happiness--
جستجو براي خوشبختي و ارتقاي خوشبختي
--is in all of this and the power of our imagination.
در تمام اينا و قدرت تخيل ماست
I'm writing a novel.
دارم يه رمان مينويسم
I don't suppose you have the time or the inclination to even read a novel.
فکر نميکنم  وقت داشته باشي يا اشتياقي به خواندن حتي يه رمان داشته باشين
I've written one. It's going to be published.
يکي نوشته ام. ميخواد اب بشه
And I'm writing another.
و دارم يکي ديه مينويسم
Can I read it?
ميتونم بخونمش؟
No-one has read It -- None of my friends.
هيکي اونو نخونده--هيکدوم از دوستام
What's it about?
موضوعش درباره يه؟
About? It has something for everyone.
درباره؟ يه يزي براي همه است
A bit like Shakespeare?
يه ذره شبيه شکسيره؟
Perhaps, yes.
شايد , آره
Please don't talk to anyone about it.
لطفا با هيکس درباره اون حرف نزن
No. Course not.
نه , البته که نه
I won't tell a soul.
مغزشو به هيکي نميم
Every human soul has seen, perhaps even before their birth...
روح هرکسي ديده شده شايد حتي قبل ار تولدشون
... pure forms. Such as justice, temperance...
به شکل ساده تر , از قبيل عدالت , اعتدال
... beauty ...
زيبايي
... and all the great moral qualities which we hold in honour.
و تمام ويژيهاي عالي اخلاقي که ما اونارو محترم ميشماريم
We are moved towards what is good...
ما بسمت اونه که خوبه ميريم
... by the faint memory of these forms.
توسط خاطره کم سوئي از اين اشکال
Simple - -and calm and blessed...
ساده و آروم و خوب
...which we saw once in a pure clear light...
که ما يکبار در نور شفاف زلالي ديديم
... being pure ourselves.
خودمون ساده باشيم
'Wholegrain'. Do we have wholegrain or something other?
جوانه هاي ذرت ما جوانه هاي ذرت يا يه يز ديه ميخوايم؟
What is whole? Is It something in itself or does it have parts?
اين جوانه يه؟ آيا يزي توشه يا اندامي داره
Oh, spaghetti.
ماکاروني
If you have a whole you have a whole.
اه تو جوانه داري تو همه ي داري
Ooh, sausages.
اوه سوسيس
You and me is a whole.
من و تو يه جوانه ايم
If you toddle off there's a hole in the whole. Or, if I do.
اه تو تصادفا بري, اونجا يه سوراخي تو جوانه است يا اه من برم
But a whole can't be broken, it just forms another whole.
اما يه جوانه نميتونه شکسته بشه اون فقط يه جوانه ديه بوجود مياره
-Baked beans.
باقالي خته
Do you want Premium points?
امتياز ويژه ميخواين؟
Do we deserve them?
ما شايسته اوناييم؟
-Do you want bags? -Bags, yes.
کيسه ميخواين؟ کيسه , بله
You know, it's all around us, people like you and me talking nonsense.
ميدوني , همه اش اطراف ما آدمايي مثل تو و من, رت و رت مين
I know, I know.
ميدونم , ميدونم
Bag for life:
کيسه مادام العمر
-For life? -That's what it says.
مادام العمر؟ اين يزيه که اونا مين
We have to ask, give you the choice.
بايد برسيم , بهتون حق انتخاب بديم
Ooh, rather.
اوه ترجيحا
You just have to listen, that's the job.
فقط بايد وش کني , اون کاره
You call it a job but it's like music, what you do.
تو اينو شغل مي نامي اما اين مثله موسيقيه ,ه کاره اي
You live with the angels, speak their language, the music of the spheres.
تو با فرشته ها زندي ميکني به زبونشون صحبت ميکني , آهن حرکت سياره ها
Nowadays the only language anyone really understands...
امروزه تنها زباني که هرکسي واقعا ميفهمه
...is pictures. Paint the picture.
تصاويره . نقاشيه تصاوير
See, now I'm bagged for life.
ميبيني , حالا مادام العمر کيسه کش شدم
Love's the only language everyone understands.
عشق تنها زبانيه که هرکسي درک ميکنه
Ooh love, yes.
اوه عشق , آره
I can read It but I can't speak it.
ميتونم بخونمش اما نميتونم صحبتش کنم
My coat's caught on your chair.
کتم به صندليت ير کرده
And the captain said as the two weevils dropped out of the biscuit...
و کايتان فت نانکه دو تا سوسک به سمت بيسکويت راهي شدن
..."which would you rather have, Mr Smith?"
کدوم يکيشو مايلي برداري , آقاي اسميت؟
"The bigger one, sir."
بزرتره , قربان
"Wrong, Mr Smith, wrong." "In the Navy you should always...
اشتباه , آقاي اسميت , اشتباه ...توي نيروي دريايي تو بايد هميشه
...choose the lesser of the two weevils."
سوسک کويکتره رو انتخاب کني
Patrick O'Brian.
اتريک اُبراين
"Between two evils always choose the one you haven't tried before."
بين دو شيطان هميشه اوني رو انتخاب کن که قبلا تجربه اش نکردي
Mea West. Oh my vest!
انجمن مديريت دريايي . اوه جليقه ام
I tore my vest again this morning.
دوباره امروز صبح جليقه امو اره کردم
You must get some new vests.
تو بايد جليقه هاي جديدي بيري
Jolly good.
خيلي خوبه
I just said that.
من که لحظه يش اونو فتم
You're always saying that you just said something. Me too.
تو هميشه ميي اونه که لحظه قبلش فته بودي . منم همينطور
Good job you reminded me I had two lectures today.
کارت درسته بهم يادآوري کردي که امروز 2 تا سخنراني دارم
You remembered.
به ياد داشتيش
No, but I remembered to apologise for the one I forgot.
نه اما به ياد آوردم براي اوني که فراموش کردم معذرت خواهي کنم
They were very sweet about it.
اونا درباره اون خيلي شيرين اند
Glad not to have listen to you, I expect.
خوشنود نيستم که بايد بهت وش کنم , انتظار دارم
Oh, I'm sure.
اوه يقين دارم
They'd have been delighted to have listened to you.
اونها خوشحال شده اند که بهت وش دادند
I always have been.
هميشه خوشحال بوده ام
-Iris! -John.
! آيريس جان
Than kyou. Keep the change.
ممنونم.بقيه اش مال خودت
-Janet. Janet! -Oh my God, Iris.
جانت . جانت اوه خداي من آيريس
Am I late?
دير کردم؟
Oh no, it's the hokie-cokie. Everything will be over.
اوه نه, همه دارند با هاکي کاکي ميرقصند
Oh, John, wait. I've got my stocking caught up.
اوه جان وايسا جورابم ير کرده
Stupid things. Really.
يز مزخرفيه , جدي
I'm not sure I'm entirely -- I'm so sorry.
من کاملا مطمئن نيستم - خيلي متاسفم
Oh, sorry.
اوه متاسفم
Cha-cha-cha.
(نوعي رقص سريع اسانيايي)
-Thank you. -You too.
مرسي تو هم همينطور
That was my husband.
اوه همسرم بود
Cha-cha-cha.
سريع تر
Are you with Iris?
تو همراه آيريسي؟
Hoping so.
اميدوارم
You know we have...
ميدوني ما داريم
I thought we had.
فکر کردم ما داشتيم
...nearly met.
تقريبا ملاقات کرديم
-Are you a friend of Iris? -Yes.
تو دوست آيريسي؟ آره
She seems to have a lot of f...
...اون به نظر مياد خيلي بامز
Janet Stone. John Bayley.
جان استون . جان بايلي
-How do you do?
طورين؟
Shall we?
ما بايد؟
What are your rooms like?
اتاقت ه شکليه؟
Adequate,thank you.
به اندازه , مرسي
I'd like to see them.
دوست دارم ببينمشون
Do you have a lot of friends?
دوستان زيادي داري؟
Is a list of my friends necessary?
ليست دوستام لازمه؟
I justwondered if you had many.
فقط شفت زده شدم اه خيلي داشتي
There aren't many people that one wants to know one.
آدمهاي زيادي نيستند که يکيشون بخواد اون يکي رو بشناسه
Iris!
!آيريس
You might fall.
ممکن بود بيفتي
Would you like some champagne?
شاماين دوست داري؟
That would be nice.
خيلي خوبه
I've had some since Christmas... It does keep, doesn't it?
از بعد از کريسمس يه ندتايي داشتم بايد مونده باشه , نمونده؟
I shouldn't be doing this.
نبايد اين کارو ميکردم؟
What?
ه کاري؟
Having women in my room. It's not permitted.
يه خانم توي اتاق داشته باشم . اجازه نداده
I wouldn't say you'd had me exactly.
نفتم که تو دقيقا منو داري
It was all right, wasn't it?
خوب بود , نه؟
Oh, I think so.
اوه اينطور فکر ميکنم
Broke the ice, so to speak.
سر صحبتو بازکن , خوب حرف بزن
-"Ice"? -What?
صحبت؟ ي؟
It'll do.
دارم همين کارو ميکنم
Aren't you particular about words at your college?
تو درباره لغات توي دانشاه سختير نيستي؟
I'm only here under sufferance really, as a tutor and guide.
من تنها کسي هستم که جدا ازم رضايت دارن به عنوان استاد راهنما و معلم
I get all the Americans and Frenchmen to mother.
تمام آمريکاييها و فرانسويها رو به اصلشون برميردونم
You love words, don't you?
تو عاشق لغاتي ,اينطور نيست؟
If one doesn't have words, how does one think?
اه يکي جن و ستيز نکنه , اون يکي ه فکري ميکنه؟
Shall I do that?
بايستي اون کارو کنم؟
What is your novel about?
رمانت درباره يه؟
About?
درباره؟
How to be free.
طور آزاد باشي
How to be good...
طور عاشق باشي
...and how to love.
و طور دوست داشته باشي
Well, that's all there is, I'd say.
خب اين تمام يزيه که من ميم
Language is all very well, you know, but...
زبان همه اش خيلي خوبه , ميدوني , اما
...it's not the only way of understanding each other.
تنها راه درک يکديه نيست
There's sight and...
ديدني هست و
...and smell and...touch, of course.
و بويايي و ...لامسه ,البته
I love your nose.
دماغتو دوست دارم
It's snub.
هن و کلفته
Snubby...
زبره
...snubby, snubby.
زبره ,زبره
it's snubby, snubby, snubby.
زبره ,زبره,زبره
Let me do that to you.
بذار اون کارو برات بکنم
Take off your jacket.
کتتو در بيار
If we were, as it were, married...
اه ما , ازدواج کرده بوديم
...we could do this all the time.
ميتونستيم هميشه اينکارو بکنيم
Perhaps?
شايد؟
We should be doing it nearly all the time.
ما بايد اين کارو تقريبا همه وقت انجام بديم
Yes, but if...
آره اما اه
Thank you.
ممنونم
Look.
ببين
I'm stopping you working.
مزاحم کارت ميشم؟
Yes, well, I don't mind.
آره,خوب,فکر نميکنم
How's it coming along?
طور يش ميره؟
It's harder to write than all the others. Much.
نوشتن اين سخت تر از اوناي ديه ست.خيلي سخت تر
Have you noticed?
متوجه شدي؟
Just that you've seemed... puzzled every now and again.
....فقط اينکه به نظر مياد بعضي وقتا يج و مبهوتي
That's it, yes.
خودشه, آره
Puzzled.
يج و مبهوت
Puzzled. It's a funny word.
يج و مبهوت .کلمه بامزه ايه
All words are like that when you take them by surprise, aren't they?
تمام لغات مثل اونند وقتي با تعجب از اونا استفاده ميکني,اينطور نيست؟
Have you got a title?
عنواني براش انتخاب کردي؟
'A lot of trees...
...درختان زيادي
...seem near.'
به نظر نزديک ميان
We must stop it.
بايد جلوشونو بيريم
What to do?
ي کار کنيم؟
The window, John, the window! We must stop it.
نجره ,جان,نجره بايد جلوشونو بيريم
No. See...
نه ,ببين
...it's gone.
تموم شد
We all worry about going mad, don'twe?
ما از ديوانه شدن نرانيم , نيستيم؟
How would we know...
...طور ميشه ما
...those of us who live in our minds anyway?
از يزايي که در ذهنمون ميذره آاهيم؟
Other people would tell us.
آدمهاي ديه بايد به ما بن
Would they, John?
بايد بن ,جان؟
I don't want to set the world...
نميخوام دنيا رو
Sorry.
ببخشيد
...on fire.
روي آتش قرار بدم
John Bayley.
جان بايلي
Haven't seen her for ages.
خيلي وقته که نديده بودمش
Jolly good -- nice.
خيلي خوبه ,مودبه
Takes all sorts. Not that I ...
...توانايي هر نوع کاري رو داره . نه من
...we're all men at St Anthony's.
ما همي توي انجمن شعر آنتوني مرد يم
Do you like women?
از زنها خوشت مياد؟
I mean, do women like you?
منظورم زنها ازتو خوششون مياد؟
You mean lesbians?
منظورت همجنس بازيه؟
Yes.
آره
Would it bother you if they did?
اه اونا انجامش بدن تورو نران ميکنه؟
Oh no, the some thing happens with me. With homosexuals, I mean.
اوه نه ,يکسري يزها عليهم اتفاق افتاده همجنس خواهي منظورمه
And do you go to bed with them?
و باهاشون به رختخواب رفتي؟
Lord no.
خدا جون ,نه
At the college... they are all, as somebody once said to me...
توي دانشاه...اونا همشون بودند نانه يکي يکبار بهم فت
..."Old fashioned lesbians of the highest type".
محافظه كار زنان همجنس راي يهودي از عاليترين نوع
And do you go to bed with them?
و آيا باهاشون تو رختخواب خوابيدي؟
-Dame Iris? -Yeah.
ديم آيريس؟ آره
It's this way.
از اين راه
She's written philosophy and plays and poetry...
اون فلسفه مينويسه , نوازنده و شعر ميه
...but her novels are her lasting literay legacy.
اما رمانهاش ميراث ادبيه جاودانيه
Iris Murdoch is acknowledged as the foremost English novelist...
آيريس مورديک به عنوان بهترين رمان نويس انليسي شناخته شده
...of her generation.
تو نسل خودش
A little excessive, don't you think?
يه کم اغراقه , اينطور فکر نميکني؟
What do you reckon, shall I take that again?
ي فکر ميکني,بايد دوباره بيريمش؟
Her novels embrace the subjects of freedom...
رمانهاش شامل مضمون آزادي ميشه
...and what it means to be good.
و ه معني داره که مهربان باشيم
And they're all studies in the successes and failures of love.
و اونها روي موفقين و شکست خورده هاي عشق مطالعه کردند
She's written philosophy and plays and poetry...
اون فلسفه مينويسه , نوازنده و شعر ميه
...but her novels are her lasting literay legacy.
اما رمانهاش ميراث ادبيه جاودانيه
People, ofcourse, are very secretive and for many reasons...
مردم ,البته ...خيلي مرموزند و به دلايل زيادي
...want to appear what they call 'ordinary'.
ميخوان به اونه که اونا "معمولي" ميخونن ,ظاهر شن
Everybody has thoughts they want to conceal.
هرکسي فکر ميکنه که اونا ميخوان مخفي کنن
Perhaps even quite simple aspects of their lives.
شايد حتي زنديشونو کاملا ساده جلوه ميده
People have obsessions and fears and...
مردم وسواس فکري و ترس و..دارن
...and passions which they don't admit to.
و تعصب شديدي, که اونا رو زير بار نميبره
I think any character is interesting and has extremes.
فکر کنم هر شخصيتي جالب توجهه و افراط داره
it's a novelist's privilege to...
...اين امتياز ويژه رمان نويسيه که
...see how odd everyone is.
هرکس قدر عجيبه
In your novels you yourself...
...توي رمانت شما خودت
...were very exacting your use of language...
خيلي به کاربرد زبان سخت ير بودي
...but in general terms, do you think the language is becoming debased?
اما در شرايط معمولي , فکر ميکني زبان تحقير ميشه؟
Reading and writing...
...خواندن و نوشتن
...and the preservation of language and its forms...
و صيانت از زبان... ...و اشکال آن
...and...
...و..
...the kind of eloquence and beauty that language is capable of...
نوع بيان... ...و زيبايي که زبان قادره
...is something terribly important to human beings...
يه يز وحشتناک مهميه... که انسان
...this is connected to thought.
به فکر متصله...
If children are not taught...
...اه به ها فکر نکنن
What did you say? Did you ask...?
ي ميفتي؟ سوال رسيدي...؟
I was asking about the importance of language.
داشتم درباره اهميت زبان سوال ميکردم
John.
جان
John. John.
جان.جان
Iris?
آيريس؟
John.
جان
-Oh, you're there. I'm back. -What is it?
اوه اينجايي. برشتم اين يه؟
-Much earlier than I thought. -Yes, I came straight  back.
خيلي زودتر از اوني که فکر ميکردم آره ,مستقيم برشتم
I didn't know why I was there.
نميدونستم براي ي اونجا بودم
You were going to do an interview.
داشتي ميرفتي مصاحبه انجام بدي
-Well,what interview? -I don't know.
خب , کدام مصاحبه؟ نميدونم
And see your publisher?
ناشرتو ديدي؟
-Was it your publisher? -So I came back.
اون ناشرت بود؟ س برشتم
I didn't expect you back for ages.
ازت توقع نداشتم به ذشته برردي
-Has Norah rung? -I didn't answer.
نورا زن نزد؟ جواب ندادم
Iris, Norah's dead.
آيريس, نورا که مرده
Oh, so she is. Oh,that is sad.
اوه ,س اون, غمناکه
Of, well, nevermind.
از خوبي , اهميتي نده
It must have been Ed.
اون بايد اد بوده باشه
What for?
براي ي؟
Oh, so I came back.
آره کتابم , س بخاطر اين  برشتم
What is...
...اسم
...the name of the Prime Minister?
نخست وزير کيه؟
-Are you asking me? -Yes, I am.
داري از من ميرسي؟ آره دارم
I know.
ميدونم
Okay, what is the name of the Prime Minister?
باشه, اسم نخست وزير يه؟
I don't know. Ask John. Surely It doesn't matter.
نميدونم. از جان برس.مسلما اهميتي نداره
Okay. Well, no, not really.
باشه,خب,نه , واقعا نه
Someone will know.
يکي ميدونه
Who would you like to see?
دوست داري کي رو ببيني؟
-I mean, is there anyone...? -I don't know.
منظورم,کسي هست که...؟ نميدونم
Shall I look up some names, talk to someone?
بايد ندتا اسم رو جستجو کنم,با يکي حرف بزنم؟
I've got a lot of ideas, but they won't come together.
ايده هاي زيادي دارم اما اونا با هم ديه جمع نميشن
It happens all the time, forgetting names.
فراموش کردن اسما, هميشه اتفاق مي افته
So, does it happens all the time?
س هميشه اتفاق مي افته؟
Does she mean "writer's block"? I suppose she does, but...
"آيا اون منظورش"انسداد فکري نويسنده مان کنم همينه ,اما
-Iris can always write, Doctor. -Oh, I know.
آيريس هميشه ميتونه بنويسه,دکتر اوه ,ميدونم
-Iris is a person of some... -Yes. But it doesn't work like that...
...آيريس کسيه که بله,اما مثل اون موقع کار نميکنه
But surely in her case, a woman with a first-class mind?
اما مسلما در سرذشتش يه زن ,با ذهن درجه يک
We'll have to be certain. There'll have to be tests, scans.
ما بايد مطمئن باشيم اونجا بايد تست بشه,بررسي شه
Well, I don't think I can... I mean it's a little beyond my competence.
...باشه, فکر نميکنم بتونم منظورم يه ذره بيشتر از صلاحيت منه
Iris finds her new book very tiring and difficult.
آيريس کتاب جديدشو بسختي و مشکلي يدا کرده
Basically, I'll arrange something.
به طور اساسي يه يزي رو سازمان ميدم
Iris has a very clear mind...
...آيريس يه ذهن خيلي شفافي داره
...mine's a muddle but not hers.
يجي ذهني داره اما نه اون
She does everything, always has. Food, shopping...
او همه ي داره, هميشه داره غذا,خريد
...tickets for things...
بليط يزها
I never know how she manages and does her books as well.
هرز نميدونم اون طور مديريت ميکنه و بخوبي کتاباشو داره
Well, they can get your help.
باشه,اونها ميتونن کمکتونو بيرن
No, nobody would suit. We're odd, you know.
نه ,هيکس درخواست نميکنه. ما نخاله ايم,ميدوني
There's a very good place, a specialist nursing home, Vale Hose.
جاي خيلي خوبي بود خانه نهداري از بيماران ويژه ,خانه سالمندان
-Not necessary. -Oh, no, not yet.
لازم نيست اوه نه ,هنوز نه
-Not your fault. I'm sorry. -I'm orry.
تقصير تو نيست.متاسفم متاسفم
Well...take care.
خب...مواظب خودت باش
Goodbye, Doctor. Thank you. Careful. Goodbye.
خداحافظ دکتر ممنونم.مواظب باش . خداحافظ
Iris!
!آيريس
I'm sure the country won't go to the dogs.
مطمئنم کشور رو به زوال نميره
Not knowing the Prime Minister's name is not a capital offence.
ندانستن نام نخست وزير که جرم نيست
-Absolutely. -I know the names that matter.
قطعا اسمهايي رو که مهم هستند و ميدونم
It'll be all right.
اونم ميتونه خوب بشه
Well, it will be if you stop worrying.
خوب ميشه اه تو نران يزي نباشي
I've got a book to finish.
يه کتاب دارم که بايد تمام کنم
...Tony Blair. So there.
توني بلر .اينم از اين
Iris, are you comfortable?
آيريس ,راحتي؟
I'm going to start the scan now. Just keep nice and still.
ميخوام اسکن و الان شروع کنم فقط مودب باش و تکون نخور
Try to relax. It'll take about fifteen minutes.
سعي کن راحت باشي حدود 15 دقيقه طول ميکشه
John.
جان
-Oh Janet. -I'm sorry.
اوه ,جانت متاسفم
Is Iris still...? I'm so sorry I'm late.
آيريس هنوز..؟ ببخشيد دير کردم
I don't know what's going to happen, Janet.
نميدونم ه اتفاقي ميخواد بيفته, جانت
I've left the car outside - the engine's running.
ماشينو بيرون قفل نکردم -موتورش روشنه
-...won't be a mo. -Right.
يه لحظه نران نباش باشه
-See you out there. -Yes.
بيرون ميبينمت آره
-John, I'm frightened. -Everyone's doing their best.
جان , ترسيده بودم هرکسي به نحو احسن کارشو ميکنه
Janet's got the car.
جانت ماشينو آورده
It will -- be...
خوب ميشي
-It's done. -You're finished?
تموم شد تموم کردي؟
I thought you were close.
فکر ميکردم آخراش باشي
So far it hasn't made any difference.
تا اينجا که هي تغييري نکرده
Here's to it.
بيا اينو بير
Must try and keep working.
بايد تلاش کنم و به کارم ادامه بدم
-You must. -I will.
بايد اين کارو کني حتما
And here's to the next one.
اين بعديشه
Just keep working, keep talking, keep the words coming.
فقط به کارم ادامه بدم به حرف زدنم ادامه بدم ,لغات خودشون ميان
Keep at it.
به کارت ادامه بده
I shall come on like a deprived animal if I can't write.
بايد مثل حيوان معصوم بجنبم اه نتونم بنويسم
Be liked a starved dog.
مثل يه س رسنه باشم
No, no, no. I'll keep you at it.
نه نه,نه تو رو از اون مييرم
I feel...
....حس ميکنم
...as if I'm sailing into darkness.
مثل اينکه دارم تو تاريکي قايق سواري ميکنم
Thing you eat with.
يزي که باهاش ميخوريم
animal
حيوان
An-im-al.
ح-يو-ان
Toothbrush.
مسواک
...no...
..نه..
Yes.
آره
Por...
....رت
No. See...
...نه ببينم
Portrait
رتره
Tennis thing.
وسيله تنيس
dog
س
Iris is getting tired, I'm afraid.
آيريس خسته شده, متاسفم
Can we have the blinds?
ميتونيم تمومش کنيم؟
Dame Iris, thank you very much. Than kyou.
ديم آيريس, ازت خيلي ممنونم. ممنونم
Well done, puss.
عالي بود, دختر
Dame Iris, thank you very much indeed.
ديم آيريس واقعا خيلي ممنونم
It's so kind of you to come, Dame Iris.
مهربونيتو نشون ميده که اومدين , ديم آيريس
Thank you, I like it. Thank you very much.
ممنونم , دوستش دارم. خيلي ممنونم
Is it any help?
آيا کمکي کرد؟
Well to us? Yes.
خوب به ما؟ آره
It's implacable.
تسليم نشدنيه
What does that mean?
اين يعني ي؟
It means inexorable.
يعني نرم نشدنيه
I know what the word means -- to me. To us.
ميدونم لغت ه معني ميده -به من .به ما
You see, words have meant everything to her.
ميبيني لغات همه يزو به اون نشان ميده
They would still mean something? Some thought?
اونا ميخوان هنوز يه يزي رو نشان بدن
It can't just be dead birds dropping.
اون فقط نميتونه رنده مرده درحال سقوط باشه
I know what it means and, it doesn't surprise me...
ميدونم معنيش يه و اون منو متعجب نميکنه
... it frightens me, but...
...اون منو به وحشت ميندازه اما...
...and then sometimes it doesn't frighten me and ...
وبعدش بعضي وقتا ...اون منو نميترسونه و
...that's just as bad because that's it winning, isn't it?
اون شبيه به بده براي اينکه اونه که برنده ميشه,نميشه؟
No, it's not...It won't win.
نه اينطور نيست...اون نميبره
It will win.
ميبره
There. It will win.
اونجا اون ميبره
That's very kind.
خيلي لطف کردين
Iris.
آيريس
Iris,wait for me.
آيريس ,منتظرم بمون
Just keep tight hold of me and it'll be all right!
فقط محکم منو بير و همه ي درست ميشه
You won't keep still!
!نميتوني آروم باشي
I can' tkeep still!
!نميتونم آروم باشم
I can't catch up with you!
!نميتونم بهت برسم
Speed up!
!تندتر بيا
Oh, good morning.
اوه ,صبح بخير
Ah, no...
.
I think it's the...
...فکر کنم اين
...person who brings the post, John!
!شخصيه که ست رو آورده,جان
-Yes, it is. -Yes.
بله خودشه بله
John! So Sorry.
جان !خيلي متاسفم
-Thank you. -Thank you very much indeed.
ممنونم واقعا خيلي ممنونم
So Sorry.
خيلي متاسفم
Go on. Go on, go on, go on...
بفرمائيد , بفرمائيد
It's only the postman.
اون فقط ستيه
-It's only the postman. -Don't repeat everything, puss.
هريزي رو تکرار نکن,دختر
It's only the postman.
اون فقط يه ستيه
It's for you -- It's your book.
براي توئه--کتابته
-What's that? -Your book.
اين يه؟ کتابت
It's only the postman.
اون فقط ستيه
It's your book.
کتابتو
-IRIS MURDOCH - JACKSON'S DILEMA -Isn't it perfectly splendid?
آيريس موردوک- جکسون ديلما کاملا باشکوه نيست؟
Why don't you look at it?
را ناهي بهش نميندازي؟
It's only the postman.
اون فقط ستيه
Oh, damn!
اه لعنتي
Stop nudging up to me like a water buffalo.
انقدر مثل يه او ميش بهم سقلمه نزن
I have a lot to do. Lots to do, Iris.
خيلي کارهاست که بايد بکنم. خيلي کارها,آيريس
See what I've done now?!
!ديدي حالا ي کار کردم؟
It's not your fault. Not your fault. Sorry, sorry.
تقصير تو نيست.تقصير تو نيست.ببخشيد,ببخشيد
-It's only the postman. -Yes, all right, it's only the postman.
اون فقط ستيه آره خيلي خب اون فقط يه ستيه
So sorry. There's lots to do.
خيلي متاسفم.خيلي کارهاست که بايد بکنم
Which side do I go?
کدوم طرف بايد برم؟
Ask me my three main priorities for Government...
ازم برسين 3 الويت اصلي ... براي دولت يه
...and I tell you...
...و من بهتون ميم...
...education, education and education.
تحصيلات ,تحصيلات,تحصيلات
John. John! Why does he keep saying that? What does he mean?
جان. جان! را داره اينا رو ميه؟ منظورش يه؟
-By what? -Education, education, education.
از ي؟ تحصيلات ,تحصيلات ,تحصيلات
I think he means learning, everyone getting enough of it.
فکر کنم منظورش ياديريه هرکسي از اون بهره ببره
Why does he keep saying it?
را اينا رو ميه؟
Politicians have to keep repeating things to make themselves heard.
سياستمداران مجبورن يزها رو تکرار کنن تا اونا وش کنن
They have to do anything to make themselves liked.
اونا بايد هرکاري کنند تا خودشونو محبوب کنند
Why does he want to eat a sheep's ear?
را اون ميخواد وش وسفندا رو بخوره؟
Shall I turn it off?
بايد اينو خاموش کنم؟
No!
!نه
We could go for a swim tomorrow, if it's not raining.
ميتونيم فردا بريم شنا اه بارون نياد
-No. -Yes, you love water.
نه آره,تو آبو دوست داري
When you swim you love it, swim? Swim is good for you.
وقتي شنا کني عاشقش ميشي,شنا؟ شنا برات خوبه
When are we leaving?
کي ما ميريم؟
Not today.
امروز نه
Are we going to London?
ميخوايم بريم لندن؟
No, we're going for a swim.
نه ميخوايم بريم براي شنا
When are we leaving?
کي ميريم؟
Not today.
امروز نه
Iris -- Iris, wait for me.
آيريس -آيريس صبرکن منم بيام
-You dirty old man! -Hello.
تو يرمرد کثيفي هستي سلام
There we go. Well done.
بفرما.خيلي خوبه
No, Iris, not with your socks on, your socks!
!نه آيريس با جورابات نه ,جورابات
No, no, give me your hand. Give me your hand.
نه نه ,دستتو بده من,دستتو بده من
Give me your hand...
...دستتو بده من
You'll pull me in. No, no...
داري منو ميکشي تو. نه نه
You're all right. I won't let you go.
حالت خوب ميشه. نميذارم بري
Let me get you dry. You're all right.
بذار خشکت کنم. خيلي خوبي
Where are your socks? Socks? No?
جورابات کجاست؟ جورابات؟ نه؟
Uppy, uppy hands. Uppy hands. Let's get it on.
بالا ,دستاتو بيار بالا دستاتو بيار بالا ,بذار خودش بره
That's it.
خودشه
Iris, come on. Just put your hand...
آيريس ,بجنب, فقط دستتو بکن تو
...like this. Up hand. Up.
مثل اين ,دستا بالا. بالا
-Let's get your head through. -Let's go now.
بذار دستات بره تو حالا بذار بره
No, let's go now.
نه حالا بذار بره
Iris, as soon as we've got your head in! Iris.
آيريس ,همينکه سرتو کردي تو ! آيريس
-Let's go now... -Put your head down.
حالا بذار بره سرتو بخوابون
Where's my petticoat?
زيروشم کو؟
Here.
اينجا
Are you sure he's expecting me?
مطمئني منتظر منه؟
Maurice.
موريس
I've brought John. You said I might...?
جان رو برات آوردم. فتي ممکنه..؟
Did I? And did you say you would?
من فتم؟ و تو فتي ميتوني؟
Yes. Well...come in.
آره ,خب ..بياين تو
-Maurice Charlton. -John Bayley.
موريس ارلتون جان بايلي
Isn't it hot?
رم نيست؟
Yes, Itis. I've got just the thing will cool.
آره هست. فقط يه يزي رفتم که خنک ميکنه
I imagine your friend Maurice is hoping to have his wicked will, is he?
تصور ميکنم دوستت موريس آرزو داره که بدانديشي کنه, داره؟
Not today, is he?
امروز نه,داره؟
You and I are much the some age, aren't we, John?
تو و من همسن و ساليم ,مه نه,جان؟
I think so.
اينطور فکر ميکنم
Does it matter?
خيلي مهمه؟
No.
نه
It's not important, is it?
اين مهم نيست ,مه هست؟
What Maurice means is that most of my real...
...منظور موريس اينه که بيشتر
...my other friends are -- older than me.
دوستهاي ديه ام بزرتر از من اند
Much older.
خيلي بزرتر
Yes, and there's a very good reason for that, isn't there?
آره , ودليل خيلي خوبي براي اون وجود داره ,مه نه؟
She likes people with a bit of a past.
اون از آدمهايي با ذشته کمي خوشش مياد
She uses them... Don't you?
اون ازشون بياري ميکشه...مه نه؟
No I don't.
نه ,نميکشم
For your novel, don't you Iris?
براي رمانت, مه نه آيريس؟
-I haven't read it -Haven't you?
اونو نخوندم تو نخوندي؟
Neither have you Maurice, so don't play games.
هيکسي نخونده موريس, س بازي در نيار
Nobody reads it.
هيکس نخونددش
The gentle lady hasn't yet bestowed her favour on anyone.
زن نجيب هنوز قلبشو به کسي نبخشيده
Iris doesn't like to talk about it. Do you Iris?
آيريس دوست نداره دراين باره صحبت کنه,مه نه آيريس؟
It's because it's full of people she knows.
بخاطر اينه که خيلي آدمه که اون ميشناسه
All these masters of thought you're so chummy with.
تمام اينا استاد فکر اند تو خيلي باهاش صميمي هستي
Bound to be. We all know. Isn't it, Iris?
مقيد باش ,همي ميدونيم.مه نه,آيريس؟
No. You can think what you like, you know nothing about it.
نه. تو ميتوني اونطور که دوست داري فکرکني هيي درباره اون نميدوني
Nobody knows but me.
هيکس نميدونه, اما من ميدونم
And -- I'm not telling.
و --بهت نميم
I thought it was as secret?
فکر کردم يه راز بود؟
I know Iris doesn't want it talked about.
ميدونم آيريس نميخواد درباره اون صحبت کنه
Come on, Iris, I'm sure we'll all recognise ourselves.
بجنب آيريس مطمئنم که ما خودمونو مي شناسيم
I don't see how you -- anyone can.
نميفهمم طور تو-- يا هرکسي ميتونه
They won't. They won't.
اونا نميبينن.اونا نميبينن
I hate that sort of thing. I won't ever do it.
از اين جور يزها متنفرم.هرز اون کارو نميکنم
I don't see the point of writing a novel that's autobiography.
غرض از نوشتن رماني که زندينامه خود آدم باشه رو درک نميکنم
There's no fun in that.
هي لذتي در اونکار نيست
They won't see themselves.
اونا همديه رو نميبينن
Don't people written about in novels always see themselves differently?
هميشه نوشته مردم درباره رمانهايشان را به ونه ديري نميبيني؟
-I'm sure they do, but... -And who was it who said:
مطمئنم اونا ميبينند اما : کي بود که ميفت
"You can use anyone you like in a novel...
...تو ميتوني از هرکسي که دوست داري در رمان استفاده کني
...as long as you drop it in somewhere that they're good in bed...
تازمانيکه اونا تو رختخواب خوبند
-...even though..." -...they might not be.
...ره ... اونا ممکنه نباشند...
Evelyn Waugh.
(اولين واق(نويسنده انليسي
"And so to bed." Samuel Pepys.
ار بتوني بخوابي.ساموئل يس
So, have you granted your favour to John?
س تو قلبتو به جان بخشيدي؟
Told him who's in the novel?
بهش بو ه کسي در رمانته؟
We have other things to talk about.
ما يزاي ديه داريم که درموردش حرف بزنيم
No-one has read my novel.
هيکس رمان منو نخونده
-No-one but the publisher. -It doesn't matter.
هيکس بجز ناشر مهم نيست
Well, it does matter, I feel let down.
خب ,مهمه,احساس يأس ميکنم
Am I not a small part of your life?
آيا من بخش کويکي از زنديت نيستم؟
You were very gallant.
تو خيلي شجاع بودي
Very stupid.
خيلي احمق
No, John.
نه ,جان
Will you come in?
ميخواي بياي تو؟
Have you been entertained?
تا حالا سررم شدي؟
Yes.
آره
All these people...
...تمام اين آدما
...and to think I chose you for your obvious lack of...
فکر ميکنن که من انتخابت کردم ...بخاطر فقدان آشکار
thought that... I thought no competition.
فکرشو بکن...فکرنميکردم رقابتي باشه
What's this?
اين يه؟
A friend made it.
يه دوست درستش کرده
Is she a cook, your friend?
دوستت آشزه؟
No, he's ap hilosopher. But his real interests are cooking and telephones.
نه اون يه فيلسوفه . اما سررمي واقعيش ختن و تلفن کردنه
I'd like you to read this.
دوست دارم اينو بخوني
I was rather afraid you might not like it.
تا اندازه اي ميترسم که ممکنه خوشت نياد
Thank you.
ممنونم
I value your opinion.
به عقيده ات احترام ميذارم
Perhaps it's time we made love?
شايد وقتشه که عشق بازي کنيم
Yes?
آره؟
Yes. That's what I thought.
آره . اون يزيه که بهش فکر ميکنم
Have you got a French letter?
کاندوم داري؟
A rubber thingy?
يه يز لاستيکي؟
Oh, good Lord, no.
اوه خداي  من , نه
Well...
...خب
...we'll just have to be careful.
فقط  بايد خيلي مواظب باشيم
I don't exactly...
...من دقيقا
Probably easier if you take your trousers off.
شايد آسونتره که شلوارتو در بياري
Yes, of course. I've never...
...آره ,البته ,من هرز
I'm a rather late starter.
يه کم دير شروع کردم
My brother used to have to...
...برادرم قبلا بايد
...tie my shoelaces for me till I was seven.
تا وقتي 7 سالم بود بند کفشمو ميبست
-I don't know if... -I do.
...نميدونم اه ميدونم
It'll all go...
...همه اش تموم ميشه
swimmingly.
به آسوني
-Help. -No, no, no.
کمک نه,نه,نه
Iris, calm down. No.
آيريس,آروم باش.نه
No. Help, help.
نه.کمک,کمک
I am trying to help you.
دارم سعي ميکنم کمکت کنم
Sorry.
متاسفم
Please don't, Iris.
لطفا شروع نکن,آيريس
You have nothing to be sorry about.
تو هي کاري نکردي که معذرت بخواي
It'd be unfair and I couldn't bear it.
اين بي انصافيه و من نميتونم تحملش کنم
We should be saying sorry to you.
ما بايد بهت بيم متاسفيم
And not just sorry, but...
...اما فقط معذرت خواهي نه,اما
Shall I read to you? Shall I?
ميخواي برات بخونم؟ ميخواي؟
Occupied in observing Mr Bingley's attentions to her sister...
...آقاي بينلي سرش رم توجه به خواهرش بود
Elizabeth was far from suspecting...
اليزابت بعيد ميدونست
...that she was herself becoming an object of some interest...
که اون خودش موضوع منظره جالبي
...in the eyes of his friend.
توي شمهاي دوستش باشه
Mr Darcy had, at first, scarcely allowed her to be pretty...
آقاي دارسي اولش داشت زورکي بهش اجازه ميداد که خوشل باشه
I wrote.
من نوشتم
Yes, my darling clever cat.
بله ,يشي باهوش عزيزم
You wrote books.
تو کتابها نوشتي
Books. I wrote.
کتابهايي که من نوشتم
You wrote novels.
تو رمانها نوشتي
Wonderful novels.
رمانهاي شفت انيز
I wrote.
من نوشتم
Such things you wrote.
اين جور يزا رو نوشتي
Special things...
يزهاي استثنايي
...secret things.
يزهاي مرموز
Do you know many secrets now, Iris?
حالا خيلي از رازها رو ميدوني,آيريس؟
You have shown me a map of Iris'...
شما يه نقشه از آيريس بهم نشون داده اين
...brain world. Empty...
دنياي مغز. خالي
You tell me that its hidden mysteries and ...
...بهم ميي که اين معماي نهانيه و
...and all the unknown life in there has gone, has been wiped.
و تمام زندي ناشناخته اش, رفته اک شده
How then...
...س طور
How can she say things with such a terrible lucidity?
طور اون ميتونه يزها رو با هوشياري وحشتناکي به؟
Which bit of the empty jungle does that come from?
که اين ذره جنل خالي از کجا مياد؟
-We don't know. -Not we. You don't know.
ما نميدونيم ما نه . تو نميدوني
Don't hide, please.
لطفا مخفي نکن
Is it not remotely possible...
...آيا اين ابدا ممکنه
...that what Iris says is of some consequence, yes?
که اونه که آيريس ميه نتيجه ميده,آره؟
yes, perhaps.
آره,شايد
So, perhaps we ought to learn her language...
س شايد ما بايد زبانشو بهش ياد بديم
...before the lights go out.
قبل ار اينکه راغها خاموش شن
The lights -- will go out.
راغها خاموش خواهد شد
Yes, of course they will.
بله البته خاموش ميشن
You all keep telling me, us, that.
تو هي داري به من, ما ميي که
I know that. She may even know that herself.
اونو ميدونم. اون ممکنه خودشم اونو بدونه
Iris.
آيريس
I'm sure you can write it. Just get one word down.
مطمئنم ميتوني اونو بنويسي کافيه فقط يه لغتو آزاد بذاري
Persevere.
شتکار داشته باشي
Iris, your notebook!
آيريس ,دفتر يادداشتت
No, Iris. No, no. Come, come.
نه,آيريس,نه,نه,بيا,بيا
That's it.
خودشه
we'll walk -- we'll read...
...ما قدم ميزنيم---ما کتاب ميخونيم
...and then you'll write. Be just like the old days.
وبعدش تو مينويسي. فقط مثل روزهاي آخر باش
It's Iris, mama.
آيريسه ,مامان
Look who's here, Iris.
ببينين کي اينجاست,آيريس
Hello. Hello.
سلام,سلام
Yes, Iris, sea.
آره آيريس ,دريا
I thought we'd walk, calm her down a bit.
فکر کردم اه قدم بزنيم .يه ذره اونو آروم ميکنه
She has an idea for a novel.
اون يه ايده براي رمانه
-Hello, Iris.
سلام ,آيريس
Talk to her, Janet.
باهاش حرف بزن ,جانت
Hello, Iris. The sea's a bit cold for swimming.
سلام ,آيريس . دريا يه ذره براي شنا سرده
Stay as long as you like, there's plenty of room.
تا اونجا که ميتوني بمون ,اينجا اتاقهاي زيادي داره
-We don't want to be nuisance... -Oh, no you're not!
ما نميخوايم مايه رنجش باشيم اوه ,نه نيستي
It's as much for mum as anyone, give her a bit of a rest.
اون بقدري ساکته که هرکسي بهش يه ذره استراحت ميده
Can't rush around these days, John, tummy trouble.
اين ند روز نميتوني جايي بري جان,معده مو آزار نده
-Is she ill? -She gets tired easily.
اون مريضه؟ براحتي خسته ميشه
She's really not...
...اون واقعا
What do we do?
ي کار بايد کنيم؟
Just talk to her.
فقط باهاش حرف بزنين
Say things to her that she can write. She can you know.
يزهايي رو بهش بين که بتونه بنويسه. اون ميتونه ميدوني
It's all right, is it, John?
اين خيلي خوبه,مه نه,جان؟
It'll get better as you get to know each other better.
بهتر ميشه طوريکه بهتر همديه رو بشناسيم
Iris has got more than one world going on inside her head...
آيريس, دنياهاي ديري توي سرش ميذره
...a secret world.
يه دنياي مرموز
Until another book comes out.
تا کتاب بعدي بيرون بياد
I'm only friend that knows of her secret world.
تنها دوستشم که راز دنياشو ميدونه
Oh, John.
اوه ,جان
No, no, it's like living in a fairy story.
نه,نه ,انار داريم تو داستان جن و ري زندي ميکنيم
I'm the young man in love with a beautiful maiden...
من يه جوونم که عاشق يه دوشيزه زيبام
...who disappears into an unknown and mysterious world...
کسيکه درون دنياي مرموز و ناشناخته ناديد ميشه
...but who always comes back.
اما کسيکه هميشه برميرده
Iris!
!آيريس
Look.
ببين
Iris, look, he's got his clothes on.
آيريس,ببين,اون داره با لباس به دريا ميره
He's got his clothes on!
!اون داره با لباس به دريا ميره
He's got his clothes on. He's got his clothes on.
!اون داره با لباس به دريا ميره.!اون داره با لباس به دريا ميره
Seems very sensible to me.
براي من که خيلي معقول مياد
-Janet, are you all right? -I'm absolutely fine, John.
جانت ,حالت خوبه؟ کاملا خوبم,جان
I thought I'd get her to sign this.
فکر کردم براش ببرم تا امضاش کنه
Anything is fine. Just get her to write.
هريزي خوبه.فقط نويسنديشو بدست بياره
Does she know anything about her past?
آيا اون از ذشته اش يزي ميدونه؟
Her career, work, friends?
شغلش,کارش,دوستاش؟
Something of a closed book.
يه يزي از کتاب محرمانه بسته
But it's there -- I know it.
اما اونجاست---اينو ميدونم
Oh, that's wonderful. Well done, puss.
اوه,خيلي شفت انيزه.خيلي خوبه,دختر
Good to see your book so well received, Iris.
تبريک ميم که کتابت خيلي خوب قبول شده,آيريس
Yes, wasn't it?
آره,شوخي ميکني؟
You thought you'd never finish it, didn't you?
فکر کردي که هرز تمومش نميکني,مه نه؟
I read her the reviews.
من اونو مطالعه کردم
You hated me doing it before.
قبلا ازم نفرت داشتي اه اون کارو ميکردم
Would you sign your new book for me, Iris?
ميشه کتاب جديدتو برام امضا کني,آيريس؟
Like postcards, do it at once or you don't.
مثل کارت ستال,اولشو امضا ميکني يا نه؟
Please?
خواهش ميکنم؟
I see an angel.
يه فرشته ميبينم
I think it's you.
فکر ميکنم اون تويي
We're undewater now.
ما الان زير آبيم
There are some drugs, aren't there, Iris?
اونجا مقداري داروئه,مه نه,آيريس؟
But they don't last long.
اما اونا زياد نميمونن
And when the friendly fog disperses...
و وقتيکه که مه مساعد متفرق ميشه
...there yawns the precipice before you, doesn't it, puss?
قبل از تو رتاه با خميازه باهات حرف ميزنه,مه نه,دختر؟
They're beautiful.
اونا خيلي زيباند
Horrible, isn't it, puss?
ترسناکه,اينطور نيست,دختر؟
Horrible thing...
يزهاي ترسناک
...when you're there with your toes at the edge of the precipice.
وقتيکه تو اونجا با انشتات  لبه رتاهي
You can say anything you like as...
...هيي نميتوني بي مثل اينکه
...long as you make it sound like it's a joke.
بعد از يه مدت يه ندايي مياد که اينا همش مسخره است
Oh, don't John, that's cruel.
اوه,نو جان,بيرحمانه است
that's where you're wrong.
اينجاست که اشتباه ميکني
It's not cruel, it's nothing...
بيرحمانه نيست,هيي نيست
...because it's not understood.
براي اينکه قابل درک نيست
She's in her own world now.
اون الان توي دنياي خودشو ماست
Which is perhaps what she's always wanted.
ه يزي ممکنه اون هميشه بخواد
Come on. Let's go in.
بجنب.بيا بريم تو
When do we go?
کي ما ميريم؟
Chin up, John.
موفق باشي جان
Janet.
جانت
Yes, puss. Yes.
آره ,دختر,آره
Going, going. No, I do go.
مردني,مردني.نه من ميرم
Soon, we'll -- we'll go soon.
بزودي,ما--ما بزودي ميريم
Now... now.
حالا--حالا
Who is it? Who is it?
کيستي؟کيستي؟
Hello, hello.
سلام,سلام
Are you there?
اونجايي؟
Where this?
اين کجاست؟
...soars enchanted...
جذاب بلند رواز
As I hear the sweet lark sing
درحاليکه آواز روش شيرين زندي رو وش ميکنم
In the clear air of the day.
در هواي اک امروز
How much is that doggy in the window?
قيمت اون سه که تو نجره است نده؟
The one with the waggly tail
اوني که دمش مثله فرفره ميرخه
I do hope that doggy's for sale.
اميدوارم که اون سه واسه فروش باشه
Sing your mother's song.
آواز مامانتو بخون
All my soul's adoration.
تمام نيايش هاي روحم
And I think he will hear me.
و فکر کنم اون بهم وش ميکنه
...soars enchanted
جذاب بلند رواز
I hear the sweet lark sing...
آواز روش شيرين زندي رو وش ميکنم
...of the day.
امروز....
It is this that gives my soul.
اين يزيه که روحمو مييره
All its joyous elation
تمام سرخوشي و شادمانيشو
As I hear the sweet lark sing
درحاليکه آواز روش شيرين زندي رو وش ميکنم
In the clear air...
...در هواي اک
...of the day.
امروز...
Dear thoughts are in my mind
ايده هاي عزيزم توي ذهنم اند
And my soul soars enchanted.
و روح جذاب و بلند روازم
As I hear the sweet lark sing
درحاليکه آواز روش شيرين زندي رو وش ميکنم
In the clear air of the day.
در هواي اک امروز
For a tender beaming smile...
...براي لبخند بشاش و لطيفم
...to my hope has been granted
تا اميدم بخشيده شه
And tomorrow he shall hear...
...و فردا اون بايد وش کنه
...all my fond heart can say
تمام قلب دوست داشتنيم ميتونه به
As I hear the sweet lark sing...
درحاليکه آواز روش شيرين زندي رو وش ميکنم
...in the...
...در...
Come, gentlemen...
بياين,نجيب زادان
...we shall have to do better than this.
ما بايد بهتر از اينو انجام بديم
aren't you a bad cat?
ربه بدي که نيستي؟
And tomorrow he shall hear...
...و فردا اون بايد وش کنه
...all my fond heart can say
تمام قلب دوست داشتنيم ميتونه به
Teletubbies!
!عروسک هاي تلويزيوني
Morning.
صبح بخير
Morning. Oh thank you.
صبخ بخير. اوه مرسي
-Okay. Bye. -Than kyou. Bye.
باشه . خداحافظ ممنونم . خداحافظ
It's only the postman.
فقط ستيه
Time for teletubbies -- Time for Teletubbies.
زمان عروسکهاست
Tinky winky Tinky Winky
.
It's only the postman.
فقط ستيه
Where have the Teletubbies gone?
عروسکا کجا ممکنه رفته باشن؟
remember Proteus?
روتئوس رو به ياد مياري افسانه يونان )خداى دريا که اشکال مختلف بخودميرفت)
-What about Proteus? -I'm like Proteus.
طور؟ من مثل روتئوسم
You've got to keep hold of me the way Hercules kept hold of him.
اينجاست که تو بايد منو بيري همونجور که هرکول روتئوس رو رفت
Even thought he changed into...
حتي اون فکر کرد که اون به
... a lion and a fish...
يه يه شير و يه ماهي
...and a snake.
و يه مار تبديل شد
I'm worried about the river, we swim.
من نران رودخونه ام ,ما شنا کرديم
You never know, sir.
شما که هرز نميدونين,آقا
I have, of course, looked everywhere here already.
البته من قبلا همه جاي اينجا رو شتم
Everything you do...
...هرکاري که ميکني
...everything you say, write...
...هريزي که ميي,مينويسي
...you do it superbly.
بسيار عالي اونو انجام ميدي...
And you're always going to, all your life...
...و تو هميشه ميخواي,تمام زنديت
...whatever you turn your hand to. I know it.
هري که از دستات استفاده ميکني. اونو ميدونم
And I know you must feel that I don't belong in your world.
و ميدونم بايد احساس کني که من به دنيات تعلق ندارم
I don't.
حس نميکنم
Between the soup and the baked beans.
بين سو و باقالي خته
Thank you so much.
خيلي ممنونم
I caught her before she got to the check-out.
من قبل از اينکه اون بميره رفتمش
She's been gone for hours...
...اون براي ساعت ها رفته بود
..I thought I'd never see her again. Never.
فکر کردم ديه هرز اونو نميبينم.هرز
Well... all's well that...
...خب...خيلي خوبه که
Please do, tell me your name?
لطفا اسمتونو به من بين؟
I'm Maurice, John.
موريس ام,جان
Iris' friend.
دوست آيريس
I was a witness at your wedding.
من يکي از حضار عروسي شما بودم
Well, I'm late for a meeting.
خب ,قرار دارم ديرم شده
-Maurice, so sorry... -So sorry.
موريس ,خيلي متاسفم خيلي متاسفم
Were you trying to get away from me?
داشتي سعي ميکردي از من دور شي؟
Did you want to leave me, Iris?
ميخواستي منو ترک کني,آيريس؟
Please?
خواهش ميکنم؟
I feel as if I don't know anything about you.
حس ميکنم به همون اندازه که من هيي درباره تو نميدونم
When you know everything about me, then I'll be dead.
تو همه ي درباره من ميدوني ,س من بايد مرده باشم
He's a Professor of Ancient History..
...اون يه روفسور تاريخ باستانه
They have a maling influence on you I think.
فکر ميکنم نفوذ بدي روي تو داشتن
They all have, all your 'friends'.
تمامشون دارن,تمام دوستات
He's a teacher, a master of thought.
اون يه معلمه,استاد انديشه
You talk, do you. You master thoughts together?
تو حرف زدي ,مه نه. تو و استاد انديشه باهمديه؟
We make love, yes, but that's not the important thing.
ما با هم عشق بازي کرديم,آره اما اين که يز مهمي نيست
Then he goes home to his wife in London.
بعدش اون رفت خونه يش زنش تو لندن
Does it frighten you?
آيا اين تو رو بوحشت مي اندازه؟
I feel as if I'm standing in a long line of suitors...
احساس ميکنم همونطوريکه ...روي خط طولاني خواستاري ايستادم
...waiting for a kind word.
منتظر يه لغت محبت آميز
I'll always give you a kind word.
هميشه بهت لغت محبت آميز ميدم
We must accept me as I am.
ما بايد بذيريم همونطوريکه من هستم
And I'm to be kept in my box or not kept at all.
و من در جعبه ام نهداري ميشم يا اصلا نهداري نميشم
Nothing matters except...
...هيي مهم نيست بجز
...loving what is good.
عاشق يز خوبي هستم
Am I good?
من خوب هستم؟
Just...
...فقط
...keep tight hold of me and it'll be all right.
فقط منو محکم بير و همه ي درست ميشه
Who are you with now, Iris?
الان با کي هستي,آيريس؟
Who is it?
اون کيه؟
We're lost.
ما شکست خورده ايم
We're lost. We're lost...
...ما شکست خورده ايم. ما شکست خورده ايم
There is no reason for this.
هي دليلي براي اين وجود نداره
And if there is I don't know it.
و اه داره من از اون خبر ندارم
I hate you Iris. You stupid cow.
ازت متنفرم آيريس. تو او احمقي هستي
I bloody loathe you.
خونخوارانه ازت بيزارم
Every bloody inch of you.
تمام خونت
All your friends have finished with you.
تمام دوستات تا آخرين کار باهات يش ميرند
Nobody else has you anymore...
هيکس ديه اي نداري
...except your fucking best friend Doctor fucking Alzheimer....
بجز بهترين دوست لعنتيت دکتر آلزايمر لعنتي
...with all his fucking gifts.
با تموم هداياي لعنتيش
I've got you now and I don't want you.
حالا من تو رو دارم و تورو نميخوام
I've never known anything about you at all...
اصلا هيي از تو نميدونم
...and now I don't care.
و حالا ديه اهميت نميدم
I think it's time I told you about...
...فکر کنم وقتشه بهت بم
...some of my friends...
...درباره بعضي از دوستام...
...the people in my past -- of my heart and...
...آدمايي توي ذشته ام---قلبم و...
...and not.
و نه...
Oh dear.
اوه عزيزم
ought I to take notes?
لازمه خلاصه برداري کنم؟
There was a friend who was a student with me.
يه دوستي بود که همشارديم بود
No, no, he can wait.
نه,نه,اون ميتونه وايسه
He was not the first person I went to bed with...
...اون اولين کسي نبود که من باهاش خوابيدم
...that was Harry..
...هري بود..
then there was Roger, who wanted to marry me...
بعد از اون راجر که ميخواست باهام ازدواج کنه
And Oscar who said he couldn't live without me...
و اسکار که ميفت نميتونه بدون من زندي کنه
...and Tom...
... و تام...
...who far too clearly could but...
...که بمراتب آشکار ميتونست اما...
So, the student friend I had resisted going to bed with...
همينطور , همشارديم ...که اصرار داشتم باهاش بخوابم
...joined the Army during the war....
... در طول جن به ارتش ملحق شد..
...and promptly asked me to marry him for...
...و بدون معطلي ازم تقاضاي ازدواج کرد...
...he was certain he was going to be killed...
اون مطمئن بود که ميخواد کشته بشه
..and wanted me to have the window's pension.
و ازم خواست که قبضهاي حقوقشو داشته باشم
Yes, I know they all said that.
آره,ميدونم اونا همشون اونو فتند
Anyway...
...بهرحال
...I didn't want to marry him...
...نميخواستم با اون ازدواج کنم...
...but I did go to bed with him.
اما رفتم باهاش خوابيدم
...I thought that best before he went off to fight, because you never know...
تا قبل از اون فکر کردم بهترينه ...اون رفت به جن,ون تو هرز نميدوني
...anyway, he, he was killed--
بهرحال,اون,کشته شد...
--my student friend...
همشارديم
...and we weren't married.
و ما ازدواج نکرديم
So no pension.
س حقوقي در کار نبود
there.
اينجا
It wouldn't have been much anyway...
اون بهرحال اينقدر زياد نبوده
I know, because I had friends killed.
ميدونم,ون دوستي داشتم که کشته شد
Their wives got very little, they get very little.
همسرانش خيلي کم مي اومدند,همسرانش خيلي کم مي اومدند
Is that all? I mean, roughly?
اين همه اشه؟ منظورم ,بطورکلي؟
What about the 'friends' in your other world?
درباره اون دوستت که توي دنياي ديه اته طور؟
You know more about me than anyone on earth.
تو خيلي بيشتر از هرکسي روي زمين درباره من ميدوني
You are my world.
تو دنياي مني
Thank you.
ممنونم
After all that I rather hoped it might be time...
...بالاخره من نسبتا اميد اينو داشتم که ممکنه زماني باشه
...for me to get my kind word.
براي من که لغت محبت آميزمو بيرم
You don't need to do it on your own. Vale House is very good.
مجبور نيستي که اينو اينجا انجام بدي خانه سالمندان خيلي خوبه
You're exhausted, you know that.
تو خسته اي,اينو ميدوني
Of course I am. It's something that we share.
البته که هستم.اين يزيه که ما باهم تقسيم ميکنيم
We're in a state of grace.
ما در ايالت زيبايي هستيم
I think we understand each other.
فکر کنم ما همديرو درک ميکنيم
What do you think?
ي فکر ميکني؟
I don'tknow. There's always help if you need it.
نميدونم.هميشه کمک وجود داره اه لازمش داشته باشي
There isn't any help for her.
هي کمکي براي اون وجود نداره
What?
ي؟
Sorry? Sorry?
ببخشيد؟ببخشيد؟
Nothing.
هيي
Why has Willie Thorne got two rabbits tattooed on his bald head?
را ويلي تورن دو تا خروش خالکوبي شده روي سر کلش ذاشته؟
I don't know, why has Willie Thorne
نميدونم,را ويلي تورن
Cos from a distance they look like hares.
براي اينکه از دور شبيه خروش صحرايي باشه
Janet's dead, Iris.
جانت مرد,آيريس
They want me to say a few words but I can't think of any.
اونا منو ميخوان که ند کلمه حرف بزنم اما به هيي نميتونم فکرکنم
Janet's dead, Iris.
جانت مرد,آيريس
I miss Janet very much.
من خيلي جانت رو دوست دارم
I miss Janet because I used to store up...
خيلي جانت رو دوست دارم ون قبلا
...funny things to tell her that happened to us.
يزهاي بامزه اي براش کنار ذاشته بودم بهش بم که اين اتفاق افتاد
...things I can no longer tell Iris.
يزهايي که ديه نميتونم به آيريس بم
Another friend visited us...
دوست ديري مارو ملاقات کرد
...in Oxford overnight recently....
اخيرا نيمه شب توي آکسفورد
...and I found her cleaning the bath.
ديدم داشت حمام رو تميز ميکرد
I said, "Oh, please, there's no need".
فتم اوه,خواهش ميکنم,ديه احتياجي نيست
She said, "Oh yes there is, I want to take a bath".
اون فت ,را هست ميخوام دوش بيرم
I was hoping to be able...
اميدوار بودم قادر باشم که
...to tell Janet that story...
به جانت اون داستانو بم
...she would have enjoyed it.
اون از اين لذت ميبرد
She would have...laughed.
اون حتما ميخنديد
I mean, I think...
منظورم,فکر کنم
...Anna Karenina, Tolstoy, you know...
آنا کارنينا,تولستوي,ميدوني
...when on her way to the station to throw herself under a train...
وقتي تو راه ايستاه بود که خودشو زير قطار رت کنه
...sees something funny which she thinks to tell Vronsky....
يه يز خنده داري ديد که اون فکر کرد به ورونسکي به
...her lover, about...
...عاشقش,درباره
...we all do it, I do it with Iris...
ما همي اينو انجام داديم,من اينو با آيريس انجام ميدم
...and Janet, all our friends...
...و جانت,تمام دوستام...
...but, then Anna thought that she wouldn't be seeing Vronsky again...
اما بعد آنا فکر کرد که... ...اون نميخواد دوباره ورونسکي رو ببينه
...because she was about to kill herself.
براي اينکه اون ميخواست خودشو بکشه
Oh, but, you don't want to hear this...
...اوه, اما شما نميخواين اينو بشنوين
...Janet didn't kill herself...
...جانت خودشو نکشت...
But, if there's one thing that would have prevented...
اما,اه يه يزي بود ...که ميخواست مانعش بشه
...Anna from throwing herself under a train...
از انداختن خودش زير قطار بود
...that would be it, the thought of telling something funny...
اين خودش بود فکر فتن يه يز بامزه
...to the man she loves.
به مردي که دوستش داشت
The love is over...
عشق تمام ميشه
...though...
...اره...
...life will...
...زندي..
...soon be over.
بزودي تموم ميشه...
That's all.
فقط همين
Goodbye, Janet.
خداحافظ ,جانت
No, no, Janet. Jan!
!نه,نه,جانت.جان
It's all right, Iris.
اون خوبه,آيريس
Wrong, wrong, wrong.
اشتباهه,اشتباهه,اشتباهه
-Wrong driving. Stop it, Iris!
راننديت اشتباهه تمومش کن,آيريس
Wrong driving!
!راننديت اشتباهه
No. Stop it, Iris.
نه ,تمومش کن ,آيريس
-Not house. Not mother.. -Iris, it's very dangerous.
خونه نه.مادر نه آيريس,اين خيلي خطرناکه
Them! Them!
!اونا!اونا
Iris!
!آيريس
Puss.
دختر
My old mouse -- My old cat mouse.
موش يرم---موش ربه يرم
Where are you?
کجايي؟
I...
من
...love...
دوستت
...you.
دارم
Ah, little mouse. I know you do.
آه ,موش کوولو. ميدونم داري
I used to be...
من قبلا
...so afraid of being alone with you...
از تنهايي با تو خيلي ترسيده بودم
...now I can't be without you.
حالا نميتونم بدون تو باشم
Let's get us -- home...
بيا بريم خونه
...and then there'll be tomorrow...
وبعدش فردا ميشه
...and the nex tday...
...و بعدش روز بعد...
...and the next...
...و روز ...
...and on we go...
...و ما
...getting closer and closest together...
...نزديک و نزديکتر ميشيم...
Oh, your ring.
اوه حلقه ات
It's so worn now.
هنوزم دستته
Where did you get it?
از کجا اينو رفتي؟
From a pawnbrokers.
از يه دلال
I like things that are worn down.
من از يزهايي خوشم مياد که تموم ميشن
Which wear and wear and wear...
که بوشم و بوشم و بوشم
...until they go.
تا تموم شن
We've had a bit of luck.
ما يه ذره شانس آورديم
Usual thing, I'm afraid -- Somebody's died.
يزهاي هميشي,ميترسم---يه کي مرده
Iris...
...آيريس
...don't you have a smile for Doctor Gudgeon?
به دکتر ودئون لبخند نميزني؟...
No?
نه؟
No.
نه
So -- the time has come.
خب---وقتش رسيده
You know it would, Professor Bayley.
ميدوني ميرسه,روفسور بايلي
Yes.
بله
She didn't have a smile for you today.
اون امروز به شما لبخند نزد
Yes. Well, we must make a start.
آره,خب,ما بايد شروع کنيم
-What do I do? -Nothing any more.
ه کاري بايد بکنم؟ ديه هيي
Vale House is a very friendly place, you know.
خانه سالمندان يه جاي خيلي دوستانه ايه,ميدوني
I was, surpr....
...من غافل
...I mean, this is one of the best.
منظورم,اين يکي از بهترينهاست
More difficult to get into than...well, Eton.
داخل شدنش خيلي سخته تا...خب,ايتون
-Taxi for Vale House? -Yes.
تاکسي براي خانه سالمندان؟ بله
Lady's on the stairs, but I can't get her down.
خانم روي لکانه,اما من نميتونم بيارمش ايين
Shall I?
ميتونم؟
You all right, my love?
شما حالتون خوبه,عشق من؟
We're going for a little drive.
ما سعي ميکنيم يه ذره رانندي کنيم
What's your name then?
س اسمتون يه؟
Iris.
آيريس
Yes, it's Iris.
بله,آيريسه
All right then, Iris...
خيلي خوب ,آيريس
...you'll be all right, my love, come on.
تو خوب ميشي,عشق من,بجنب
Come on, upsy-daisy.
بجنب,تو ميتوني
There you go.
بفرمائيد
Lovely.
دوست داشتنيه
Human beings love each...
آدما عاشق همديه ميشن
...in sex -- in friendship...
توي سکس--توي دوستيهاشون
...and when they're in love.
و وقتي اونا عاشق ميشن
And they cherish other beings...
و اونا به موجودات ديه احترام ميذارن
...humans -- animals, plants...
...انسان--حيوانات,ياهان...
...even stones.
حتي سنها...
She'll be fine now, won't you Iris?
اون حالا خوب ميشه,مه نه آيريس؟
You can visit any time you like...
شما هروقت که دوست داشتين ميتونين ملاقاتش کنين
...come all day if you want to.
تمام روز رو بياين اه دوست داشتين
Stay the night, that's all right...
...شب بمونين,اشکالي نداره
...we can make arrangements for you to do that anytime.
ما ميتونيم ترتيبي بديم براي شما که هروقت خواستين انجامش بدين
It was so quiet...
...اون خيلي ساکت بود
...when she died.
وقتيکه  مرد...
Do you know, I thought I wouldn't mind doing that myself..
ميدوني فکر کردم نميتونم اون کارو خودم بکنم
I had a joke to tell her.
بهش يه جوک فتم
It wasn't a very good one but she'd have laughed.
از نوع خوبش نبود اما اون خنديد
We need to believe in something divine.
ما لازمه به يه يز الهي ايمان داشته باشيم
Without the need for God.
بدون نياز به خدا
Something we might call love...
...يه يزي که ما ممکنه بهش بيم عشق
...or goodness.
يا نيکي...
As the psalm says...
...همونطور که سرود روحاني ميه
..."Whither shall I go from thy spirit...
...جايي که ميتونم از روحت برم...
...whither shall I flee from thy presence?
جاييکه ميتونم از يشاهت فرار کنم؟...
If I ascend unto Heaven thou art there...
...اه من به بهشت رواز کنم تويي که اونجايي
...if I make my bed in Hell behold thou art there.
اه من تختمو تو جهنم مرتب کنم ببين تويي که اونجايي
If I take the wings of the morning...
...اه من بالهاي صبحاهي رو بيرم
...and dwell in the uttermost parts of the sea...
...و در بالاترين قسمت دريا ساکن شم...
...even there shall thy hand lead me...
... حتي اونجا ميتونه ژرف يابت منو يدا کنه...
...and thy right hand shall hold me."
و دست کمکت ميتونه منو بيره